DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宫饭》
How boring is this?
太无聊了吧
You got that right.
说得对
Take this, will you?
拿这个过去 好吗？
It's good!
好好吃
It's good.
的确好吃
When we enter the dungeon again,
等我们再次潜入迷宫
we won't be able to have delicious food for a while.
会有好一阵子吃不到这种美食吧
Better savor it well, then.
要趁现在好好品尝
Hey, Kabru!
喂 喀布尔
How're you doing lately?
你最近过得怎么样啊？
Seems like you're doing well.
我看你混得很好呢
Nah, we still have a long way to go.
没有啦 我们还有很大的进步空间
Until just a while ago, you were just fledglings.
你们不久前都还只是菜鸟
But now you have an air of confidence.
最近倒是散发老手的自信了
On the other hand, none of the other big parties…
反观那些大队伍…
are faring so well.
全都萎靡不振
Is that so?
是那样吗？
Missing persons. Falling outs.
下落不明、起内讧
Oh, and trouble over money matters.
对了 还有金钱上的纠纷
To everyone's surprise, it might be folks like you
搞不好最后会是你们这种人
who end up defeating the lunatic magician.
出乎意料地打倒疯狂魔法师
Oh, no.
不 怎么可能
I'm not sure about that.
这很难说啦
So you say, but you just might!
那么谦虚 其实办得到吧
-You gave him a polite smile. -Huh?
-陪笑脸 -什么？
Instead of putting on a polite smile and being noncommittal,
你不必用陪笑脸敷衍过去
you should have told him clearly.
直接跟他说清楚不就好了
"Of course, we'll be the ones to defeat the magician."
“我们当然会打倒那个魔术师
"We won't become adventurers like you who live from hand-to-mouth."
才不会变成像你们那样 过一天算一天的冒险者”
Rin…
铃…
Let's show them with action rather than words.
与其用嘴巴说 不如身体力行 做给他们看
So, we'll venture a little deeper this time.
所以说这次我们要到更深的地方冒险
Let's make careful preparations.
认真做好准备吧
Welcome.
欢迎光临
A week's worth of food for six people and water for two days.
请给我六人份 一星期的粮食和两天份的水
Here you go.
谢谢惠顾
Food is a trickier issue than monsters when venturing into the lower levels.
要潜入深层的话 粮食是比魔物更让人头痛的问题
Just a week's worth of food is this heavy.
光是七天份就这么重
I wonder how people manage when they go underground for a month.
不晓得潜入一个月的人是怎么做的
Mickbell,
米克贝尔
let me tell you how.
就让我来告诉你吧
They eat other adventurers they meet in the dungeon!
他们是抓在迷宫遇到的 其他冒险者来吃啊
It's probably easier to hunt monsters than attack humans.
猎捕魔物感觉比攻击人类简单多了
I sure don't want to end up like them.
我可不想落得那种下场
I've never been to this floor before, but it's not that hard.
虽然是第一次来这层 但是不怎么辛苦呢
At this rate, we could probably go even deeper.
照现况似乎可以走得更深
You have a point, Rin, but let's be careful.
你说得没错 铃 不过大家还是要谨慎前进
You never know what might happen here.
我们永远不知道这里会发生什么事
I've heard that things have been strange inside the dungeon recently.
我听说最近迷宫的样子不太对劲
Monsters are more active than usual,
魔物的活动比平常更活跃
and the dungeon's layout is shifting.
而且迷宫的形状也会改变
Something unusual is happening, that's for sure.
可以确定的是肯定出现了某种异状
Let's keep our guard up.
大家千万要小心
Hey!
快看
Kabru, look what I found!
喀布尔 我在这家伙身上找到东西了
Open it.
打开吧
It's just going to be a waste of time again.
又在浪费时间做那种事
You never know. There might be a stack of gold coins inside.
说不定里面装了一堆金币
Like we ever discovered anything valuable in those.
我们从来没发现过有价值的好东西啊
It's something a zombie was carrying as if it were a treasure,
这可是丧尸死命抱在怀里的东西
quite literally.
就如同字面上的意思
It wouldn't hurt to take a peek inside.
让我们看一眼也没关系吧
Huh?
不会吧？
What is it?
是什么？
Whoa! Look at all that gold, silver, and gems!
天啊 是大量的金银珠宝
-Wow! -Awesome!
-天啊 -太棒了
Can I have some?
我可以拿走吗？
Money, so much.
钱 好多啊
I thought all the treasure in this place had already been looted.
我以为这附近的宝物早就被抢光了
Maybe this is one of the strange things happening inside the dungeon.
这也是迷宫的其中一个异状吗？
In any case, it's a big help.
不管怎么说 算是帮了我们大忙
Venturing into the lower levels is quite expensive, after all.
毕竟进入深层的开销很大
All right. Let's call it a day for now and return to town!
好 这次就到此为止 回城镇吧
-Yeah!
-好
Looks like a party got wiped out here.
有一支队伍在这种地方全灭耶
Oh dear. Seems like they were on their way back to town.
天啊 看起来他们 是在回城镇的路上出事
The poor things.
真是可怜
I don't see any visible injuries.
他们都没有什么外伤
Maybe they were attacked by a type of ghost.
是被幽灵之类的攻击了吗？
Maybe they starved.
他们可能是饿死了
No, I think they had a quarrel over money.
不 就我看来像是金钱纠纷
The corpse retriever will probably find them soon,
这群人大概很快 就会被尸体回收商发现
but I'll pray for them so they don't become zombies.
但我还是祈祷一下好了 免得他们变成丧尸
I can't do it the way Falin does, though.
虽然我没办法做到像法琳那样就是了
What should we do with their scattered stuff?
这些散落一地的遗物要怎么处理？
Let's gather them in one spot.
帮他们集中到一处吧
I bet they'll end up in the corpse retriever's pockets, though.
反正会进到尸体回收商的口袋里面吧
Huh? What was that for?
怎么了？干吗突然出声？
I-It's nothing.
没事啦
My sword suddenly jumped.
我的剑突然跳了起来
What's going on? It was calm until now.
怎么回事？之前明明很安分啊
Hey, don't wrap around my fingers!
住手 不要缠上我的手指
"Draw me!"
“把我拔出来”
It feels like that's what it's saying!
对方好像是在对我这么说
Marcille! Get away from the bodies!
玛露希尔 离尸体远一点
Huh?
什么？
Stunning magic, huh?
是用了昏迷魔法吗？
Thank goodness it wasn't an explosion.
幸好不是爆炸
Ow!
天啊
Ugh, what the heck?!
天啊 什么东西？
They're all Treasure Bugs! Gross!
这些全都是宝物虫 有够恶心
I see.
原来如此
So they were all wiped out by Treasure Bugs.
所以他们是被宝物虫害得全灭
I haven't seen them around lately, so I didn't realize.
最近我很少见到 所以都没发现
What? You did realize, though.
什么意思？明明是你察觉的啊
Yeah! How did you know?
对啊 你怎么会知道？
Um…
这个嘛…
I thought… it moved.
当时觉得那东西好像动了
My sword, I mean.
是我的剑发现的
It's already calm again.
这家伙已经静下来了
It probably responded to the Treasure Bug, right?
果然是对宝物虫起了反应吗？
If that's the case…
可是那样的话…
He's becoming less and less human.
他越来越不像个人类了
There.
这边
No!
不要啊
He's really sorting them out.
他挑得好认真
These are edible.
这边的能吃
And these aren't.
另一边的不能吃
Do they taste good, though?
这些虫好吃吗？
Of course.
当然了
Bugs are an excellent source of nutrition.
虫的营养价值很高 是很棒的食物
They have a delicious taste and flavor, too.
滋味与风味绝佳
And they look good as well.
而且外观也赏心悦目
Don't show its underside to us.
别把背面对着我们
How can you tell whether they're edible or not?
要从哪里区分能不能吃？
It depends.
取决于是什么
This one is easy to tell.
像这个就很好分辨
The necklace has legs growing between its segments.
项链在每一节之间有长脚
With brooches and coins, you look at their underside.
胸针和硬币要看背面判断
It's interesting how Coin Bugs have different designs based on their sex.
硬币虫雌雄图案不同 真有趣
Rings have a springy shank.
戒指在圆圈的部分有弹性
With tiaras, dunk them in water, and you can tell them apart easily.
王冠只要放进水里就能马上知道
If they float, they're Treasure Bugs.
浮在水面上的就是宝物虫
They're light, after all.
因为体重很轻
Anyway, let's cook them while they're still senseless.
总之趁虫子们还在昏迷状态时 开始做料理吧
To improve their texture,
珍珠蜈蚣的口感不太好
remove the legs from the pearl centipedes.
所以把脚拔掉
Then, skewer and grill them.
再串起来烤
Heat some oil and cook the underside of the Coin Bugs.
热好油锅后 把硬币虫的腹部朝下加热
Salt them lightly,
稍微撒点盐
and coat them with oil as you stir them.
拌一拌让油均匀沾附
There!
好了
It looks nice if you flip them with their backs facing up.
翻转一下 背部朝上摆盘就很好看
For the tiara, remove the eggs and larvae,
从王冠取出卵和幼虫
shatter the nest, and stew together.
把巢捣碎 一起熬煮
Put them in a jar…
然后将其放进罐子里…
And it's done!
就完成了
NATURAL AND TASTY TREASURE BUG SNACKS
（天然美味的宝物虫点心）
It looks nice, but it doesn't really whet my appetite in more ways than one.
看起来是很漂亮啦 但在各方面都提不起食欲啊
That said, I have eaten a Coin Bug before.
说是这么说 我以前倒是吃过硬币虫
There are local cuisines like this.
有类似的乡土料理
It looks lucky, and it's supposed to bring good fortune.
因为外观很吉利 可以讨个好彩头
It's way better than the one I had a long time ago!
这比我以前吃到的好吃多了
Of course, it is.
那是当然的
Monsters inside the dungeon generally taste better than those outside.
迷宫里的魔物多半比在外面的好吃
If you keep them outside, their flavor quickly deteriorates.
在外面饲养 味道就会变质
It's gooey.
黏黏糊糊的
I can't wear necklaces anymore.
我再也不敢戴项链了
They're like small fish and pretty tasty.
这些尝起来像小鱼 好好吃
The same monster will taste better when they're from the lower levels.
即使是同样的魔物 越深层的越好吃喔
I can't wait to try it.
我很期待
Thank you.
谢谢
It's sweet and delicious.
甘甜美味耶
They really look just like gems.
看起来真的和宝石一模一样
In the context of concealing itself from enemies through camouflage,
借由伪装成别的物品 在敌人面前隐身
it's one of your kind.
就这点来说是你的同伴
Is that why you responded?
所以你才起反应吗？
Wait…
等等…
Give me one.
给我一块
Nothing.
没事
That was intimidation.
这是威吓行为
Did it try to defeat the bug with me because it thinks I'm a friend?
是把我当成伙伴 想和我一起打倒虫子吗？
You cute thing!
可爱的小家伙
Let me give you a name.
帮你取个名字吧
Let's get going soon.
差不多该走了
Can I throw away the inedible ones?
这些不能吃的可以丢掉吗？
If you want.
丢掉无妨
What happens if you eat the inedible ones?
不能吃的那些吃了会怎么样？
Do they taste bad? Or are they poisonous?
会很难吃？还是有毒？
What are you talking about?
你在说什么啊？
You can't possibly eat real gems.
真正的宝石本来就不能吃啊
Real gems…
真正的宝石…
Gems…
宝石…
-You should have said that first!
-你怎么不早说啦
I know! Your name is Kensuke!
我想到了 就帮你取名叫剑助
You're still munching on that?
你怎么还在吃那个？
It's heartier than it looks.
量比我想的还多
Seriously, you're making it hard to keep my guard up.
受不了 害我都松懈下来了
It suddenly got cold.
气温突然下降了
That white hazy thing…
那团朦胧的白光…
That's a lot of ghosts.
是大量的幽灵
Let's go. It wouldn't do for us to be spotted.
快走吧 要是被发现就糟了
Ghosts?
幽灵？
They must've gathered, attracted by the corpses.
大概是被尸体吸引 聚集过来的
Can't you simply use magic to…
那种东西用魔法一下子就能…
Right. Falin isn't with us.
对喔 法琳不在啊
I miss her, too.
我也好想念她
It was the least I could do, but I prayed for them.
至少我刚才祈祷了一下
So I don't think the ghosts will possess the bodies there…
所以幽灵应该不会 附在那些尸体上面…
There's one behind us.
在我们身后有一个
Run!
快跑啊
Stupid!
笨蛋
My ears…
我的耳朵…
Hurry! Before another one comes!
动作快点 另一个要来了
Looks like that noise attracted their attention even more.
刚才的声响好像引来更多幽灵了
Don't you know other magic besides something so flashy?
你只会那么招摇的魔法吗 玛露希尔？
Something random like the stuff Falin used would have done.
像法琳那样随便弄就好了
Random? Don't you know how advanced her magic was?
随便弄？你不知道 她用的是多么高等的魔法吗？
Falin, Laios' sister,
法琳就是莱欧斯的妹妹
was good at dealing with ghosts.
她对付幽灵很有一套
Lifgant Ardinbam.
利夫甘特阿丁巴姆
There! That should do it.
好 这样就没问题了
Ghosts can't harm you anymore.
幽灵伤不到你了喔
Isn't it easier to blow up ghosts when they show up?
幽灵那种东西 等到冒出来再打飞不是比较快吗？
It should be easy with your magic, Falin.
用你的魔法就能轻易做到啊 法琳
I'd rather not do stuff like that.
我会尽可能避免那么做
A dispersed ghost will simply return to its normal state over time.
消散的幽灵 过一段时间后还是会恢复原状
It causes them unnecessary suffering.
所以只会让幽灵白白地受苦
How sweet of you.
你真善良
I admire your principles, but…
我是很欣赏你的那份信念啦…
Those who steal another person's body…
但对于那些偷取他人身体的家伙…
deserve some punishment, don't you think?
也需要给点惩罚吧？
He's one of the missing adventurers.
他是寻人启事上的其中一个冒险者
All right. Give me a moment.
好 等我一下
I'll neutralize him and…
我这就让他无力攻击…
Let me handle it. There's no need to harm it.
让我来吧 没有必要伤害对方
Wait, Falin! Don't do anything reckless!
慢着 法琳 不要鲁莽地乱来
I'm sorry. Please return him.
对不起 请将他的身体归还吧
Falin!
法琳
Seems like she was an important person.
听起来她是个重要人物
Yeah. Falin was really amazing.
没错 法琳真的很厉害
If the ghosts catch up with us,
如果我们被幽灵追上的话
I'll have to do something with my magic.
只能用我的魔法想办法了
Forget it!
劝你住手
Are you planning to explode all those ghosts individually?
面对那么多的幽灵 你打算一个一个炸掉吗？
So, I should do what Falin did, right?
所以像法琳那样做就行了吧？
Make them explode with a gentle embrace.
像温柔的拥抱般炸掉那些家伙
-Make them explode with… -No way! You couldn't possibly!
-像温柔的拥抱般… -不可能 你绝对办不到
You said yourself you can't do it the way Falin does it!
你自己也说过了 坦承没办法做到跟法琳一样的事
Falin wouldn't say that, though!
如果是法琳 才不会说那种话呢
Anyway, what if you run out of magic?
而且如果你把魔力用完了要怎么办？
That's why I'm trying to make them explode with the minimal amount of magic needed!
所以我才想尝试 用最少的魔力炸掉幽灵啊
And I'm saying you can't do that!
我就是说你做不到啦
Hey, both of you…
喂 你们两个…
Turns out it's not that easy to run from the dead.
看来果然无法轻易甩掉死人
Right.
是啊
They'll catch us if we bicker in a place like this.
我们在这种地方继续争吵下去 会被对方追上的
Wait, what are you doing?
等等 你在做什么？
I'll prepare a charm to drive away the ghosts.
老夫要准备驱除幽灵的避邪物
A charm?
避邪物？
Holy water.
就是圣水
You had that on you?
你有带那种东西啊？
No. I'm going to make it now.
没有 现在要开始动手做
Make it?
动手做？
Are you a priest or something?
你难道是神职人员？
There are many customs around the world to ward off different demons.
这世上有各式各样用来驱魔的习俗
For example, lighting a fire.
比如说生火
Fire drives away the darkness and has the power to create and take.
火焰能驱散黑暗 有创造与夺走生命之力
Everywhere and throughout the ages,
古今中外
fire has been used to ward off demons and as something holy.
人们皆把火视为 避邪物或神圣之物使用至今
That's true,
确实是没错
but will the light of a candle ward off ghosts?
但光靠烛火能驱除幽灵？
While each may be weak on their own,
即使个体单独的力量薄弱
together in large numbers, they can become a substantial force.
只要聚集一定数量 也能成为强大的力量吧
Another example is the golden beetle.
像是黄金甲虫
Its characteristics led to it being worshipped
其特性被视为太阳与太阳神的象征
as a symbol of the sun and its deity.
因此受人尊崇
Another example is alcohol.
另一个例子是酒
It's an essential offering to a god and possesses disinfective properties.
那是献给神的重要供品 同时也有杀菌作用
Another example is salt.
然后还有盐
There are customs that use it to drive away evil and cleanse oneself.
习俗上会用来消灾解厄和净身
Sugar is similar to that, so I'll add some just in case.
跟盐很像的砂糖也放进去好了
It's probably less effective, so I'll add a lot.
效力感觉比较弱 所以放多一点
You're totally winging this!
你超随便的耶
Aside from that, there are herbs
其他像是香草
and the internal organs of creatures.
以及生物的内脏
Add the power of fire to this and…
这些加上火的力量…
We have holy water!
圣水就完成了
SPECIAL FUSION HOLY WATER
（特制无国籍风圣水）
Here they come!
幽灵来了
Tightly seal the jar of holy water and…
把装了圣水的瓶子牢牢密封起来…
Seal?!
密封？
Aren't you going to use it?
你不用吗？
Be patient.
不要急
Then, tie it with string…
再用绳子绑起来…
At this rate…
这样下去会…
Oh no…
不行了…
Falin.
法琳
That day, if only she didn't shield me…
那时你为了保护我 奋不顾身…
If I were the one devoured by the dragon instead,
要是被龙吃掉的是我
this sorry mess would never have happened.
就不会有如此没出息的结局了
Forgive me.
原谅我
Huh?
什么？
For a moment just now, I saw my dead dad beyond the river.
刚才有一瞬间 我看到死掉的老爸站在河岸对面
W-What on earth?
那是怎么回事？
The ghosts that come in contact with the jar of holy water are dispersing.
幽灵碰到圣水瓶就烟消云散了
That holy water is doing the trick, huh?
那个圣水还真的有效？
That actually works?
用那种东西也行啊？
Maybe we were being possessed…
我们说不定是被附身了
by Falin.
被法琳给附身
How could you say that?
你怎么能这样讲？
Falin would never do such a thing.
法琳绝对不会做那种事
She isn't a ghost yet in the first place!
再说她根本还没变成幽灵
No, that's not what I meant.
不 我不是那个意思
We shouldn't say stuff like, "Only Falin could have done this,"
我们不该觉得 “这件事只有法琳才办得到”
or "Things would've been easier if Falin was around."
“如果法琳在的话就会更加轻松”
Right now, it's just us.
因为现在就只能靠我们自己
So we have to take care of things on our own.
必须靠自己的力量设法解决
You're right.
你说得对
Senshi!
先西
Let me help.
也让我帮忙吧
It's over.
结束了
I-It's completely covered in frost!
结了好厚的霜
Using it like this is more effective than scattering it, don't you think?
用这方法比撒圣水更有效 对吧？
True.
确实如此
Ghosts can pass through walls,
既然幽灵能穿过墙壁
so it won't matter if the jar is sealed or not.
有瓶子和盖子好像也没差别
But what is this?
不过这是怎么回事？
You made ice cream.
做成冰淇淋了
EXORCISM SORBET TO DRIVE AWAY EVILS
（祈求解厄的除灵雪酪）
Is it safe to eat something that came in contact with so many ghosts?
这种碰到幽灵那么多次的东西 吃了不会有事吗？
And consuming such potent holy water could cause problems as well.
把如此强效的圣水吃下肚 感觉也会出问题
I think I'm taking too much sugar today.
老夫觉得今天好像摄取太多砂糖了
It's good!
真好吃
You're right. It's good!
真的耶 好好吃
It tastes really fresh!
味道好清爽
Seems like we managed to drive away the ghosts without making them too upset.
看来我们在没被记恨的情况下 成功驱除了幽灵
True!
是啊
You added the internal organs of a creature.
你曾说里面放了生物的内脏
What creature?
是放了什么？
I added some Slime shavings.
老夫削了史莱姆放进去
So that's why it jiggles a little.
所以才会有点弹性啊
I love how smooth the texture is.
我喜欢这种柔和的口感
This… makes me think…
这让我觉得…
If Falin were here, we probably couldn't have had such tasty food.
如果法琳在的话 现在就吃不到这么好吃的东西了
Huh?
什么？
Are you saying…
你是在说…
you're glad Falin ended up that way?
你很庆幸法琳遇上那种灾难？
Is that what you're saying? Now?!
你刚才是那个意思吗？
Huh? No, I was just…
什么？没有啦 我只是…
There are things you should say and things you shouldn't.
有些话能说 有些话不能说喔
If only Falin were here right about now.
这时如果法琳在的话就好了
He meant to say every cloud has a silver lining.
你是想表达祸兮福所倚吧
She'd say something like that to clarify what I meant!
她会像这样帮我好好澄清
Your bond with your friends is what really grew cold, huh?
真正冷掉的是你与伙伴之间的情谊？
Please return soon, Falin!
拜托你快点回来吧 法琳
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻译：梁雪莹